陛下
Majesty.
牧师不可结婚
I will have no married priests.
陛下 赫福德大人求见
Your Majesty. My Lord Hertford desires an audience.
赫福德
Hertford.
陛下 接到传自法国的消息
Your Majesty. We have received news from France.
萨里伯爵于布洛涅旁的圣艾蒂安
The Earl of Surrey, while rashly attacking.
轻率出击法国补给军
French supply forces at Saint-Etienne, just beyond Boulogne,
已损兵过六百
has lost over 600 men,
包括军官与士兵在内
as well as all the captains and gentlemen,
出于某种原因 萨里伯爵将他们置于前线
who, for some reason, he had placed in the front line.
各位大人 我从各种渠道听闻
My lords, I have heard from several sources.
布洛涅战事的惨状
of the calamitous events in Boulogne.
听说我方的萨里伯爵
It seems my Lord Surrey.
与一支庞大的法国护卫队兵戎相见
gave battle to a large convoy of French,
并遭遇惨败
and was soundly defeated.
数名军官和麾下士兵阵亡
With the death of his captains, and most of his gentlemen.
我告诫过他休要莽撞行事 休要将布洛涅
And all of this, despite my warnings not to.
置于险境 但他依然充耳不闻
be bold and place Boulogne at risk.
因此
Therefore,
我已命萨里伯爵回国
I have commanded my Lord Surrey to return here,
接受各位大人对其不当行为的审查
to be examined as to his conduct by Your Lordships.
与此同时
In the meantime,
我将任命赫福德大人作为其替任
I will appoint you, my Lord Hertford, as his replacement.
你即刻前往布洛涅
You leave at once for Boulogne.
同时 因我的秘书莱斯利先生
I have also decided.
业绩卓越 才华横溢
for his many great works and talents,
我决定委任他大法官一职
to appoint my secretary, Mr. Risley, Lord Chancellor,
并授予他莱斯利男爵称号
and to create him Baron Risley.
陛下如此信任
I am touched…
微臣感怀在心 倍感荣耀
and deeply honored by Your Majesty's trust.
- 萨福克公爵有话要讲吗 - 启禀陛下
- My Lord Suffolk? - Majesty,
有传言说大量法军舰队
there are rumors of a large French fleet.
正为作战屯兵整装严阵以待
being assembled and fitted out for war.
并且 罗马皇帝已下令在低地国家
So… the Emperor has ordered all English ships and.
拘留所有英国船只 没收所有英属财产
properties in the Low Countries to be seized.
我方应如何应对
How shall we respond?
罗马皇帝
The Emperor…
天呐
my God.
我对朋友抱诚守真竭诚相待
When I think of my fidelity to my friends.
但他们却都背信弃义言而无信
and all of their betrayals?
- 舰队正在集结 - 大人
- Fleet being amassed… - My Lord.
赫福德大人
My Lord Hertford.
- 赫福德大人 - 阁下有何见教
- My Lord Hertford. - Excellency.
能否私下交谈片刻
May we speak a moment, privately?
何事
Well?
看起来在陛下的疆域中
It seems, alas, that many things are amiss.
诸事皆生差池
in His Majesty's kingdom.
何事
What things?
战事屡战屡败 陛下负债累累
The bad harvest and the burden of His Majesty's debts.
陛下的舰队遭疫病之害
The plague among the sailors of His Majesty's fleet.
水手们焦头烂额 溃不成军
with their swollen heads and decayed ships.
阁下 您所言究竟为何
Pray, Excellency, what is your point?
由于国王轻率出击布洛涅
The poisoning and the poverty.
并且无法维持对该地的统领
of the King's realm.
致使其疆土之上
is in every way due to his rash.
哀鸿遍野 民不聊生
and unsustainable occupation of Boulogne…
正如大人您所愿
As Your Lordship would want.
我极力反对此役 这千真万确
It is true that I argued against the war.
但我在激辩中败下阵来
But I lost the argument.
大人 您失之于战
You lost the argument for war, my Lord.
但能取之于和
But you can win it for peace.
力劝国王休要无视箴言
Persuade the King of his folly in hanging on to Boulogne.
一意孤行屯兵布洛涅
against all reason.
你我也许能在一定程度上达成一致
You and I may come to some agreement.
- 大人留步 - 莱斯利先生
- My Lord. - Mr. Risley.
恭贺升迁之喜
You are to be congratulated.
谢谢您 大人
Thank you, Your Grace.
这次升迁突如其来
I confess I find this sudden elevation.
实在令我出乎意料
beyond my imagining.
非也
No!
这应在您意料之中
But you must imagine it,
并且您应同我等一样喜从中来倍感欢欣
and take great pleasure in it, as we do.
因为这必定意味着吾等之大业将蒸蒸日上
For surely, this must mean that our cause is in the ascendancy,
陛下将更加坚定地倾向
and that His Majesty tends ever more firmly.
正统宗教天主教 反对宗教改革
towards the Orthodox and Catholic persuasion and against Reform.
在下相信大人所言非虚
Well, I trust Your Grace is right.
但以在下的浅识薄见来看
But for my own part,
国王仍反复无常捉摸不定
I still find the King so changeable,
不知他是否知晓自己的意图
I wonder if he knows his own mind.
- 亨利 - 父亲
- Henry! - Father!
过来
Come here!
能在宫廷见到你真好
Oh, it's good to see you back at Court.
我很记挂你
I missed you.
你记得布丽吉特吗
You remember Brigitte?
当然 日安 小姐
Yes, of course! Bonjour, Mademoiselle.
日安 亨利 很高兴再次见到你
Bonjour, Henry. I'm very happy to see you again.
罗塞洛小姐现在是我的正式情人
Mademoiselle Roussello is now my official mistress.
她在宫廷出现令你的母亲公爵夫人
I am sorry to hear that.
郁郁寡欢 听闻此事我深表遗憾
her presence at Court makes your mother, the Duchess, unhappy.
但我也无能为力
But there is no help for it,
因为你的母亲让我很长时间都心灰意冷
for your mother has made me unhappy for a long time.
- 可怜的亨利 - 没事 他年岁已足 应知真相
- Poor Henry… - No. He's old enough to know the truth.
并了解关于爱的其他事情
And guess other things about love.
小姐
Mademoiselle,
若您能令吾父喜逐颜开 吾亦会欢欣展颜
if you make my father happy, then you have also made me happy.
瞧见了吧
See?
他比外表看起来更成熟睿智
He's older and wiser than he looks.
你也是如此
So are you.
没错 去畅饮一番
Right. Drinks.
陛下圣体可还安康
How is Your Majesty?
这么告诉你吧 凯特
I'll tell you this, Kate.
在法征战时我英姿勃发
I felt ten times better in France.
十倍于我往昔
than I have these past years since.
我最为痛恨的
What I hate above everything.
便是对事实的曲解
are the interpretations.
我在宫廷与谁交谈都是一样
It doesn't seem to matter who I talk to at Court.
大使 牧师
Ambassadors, clerics,
抑或朝臣
courtiers…
他们都从自己的利益出发
They all interpret the facts.
曲解事实
to suit themselves.
至于我 上帝知晓 我总是公正而诚实
For myself, God knows I've always spoken with candour and honesty.
但现在我深陷阴谋诡计
But all about me now is guile,
虚伪欺诈之中
hypocrisy, and dishonesty.
陛下 我写了本书
Your Majesty, I have written a book.
可否向您展示
May I show it to you?
书 什么书
A book? What kind of book?
书名是《一个罪人的耶利米哀歌》
It's called Lamentations of a Sinner.
- 陛下请看 - 请读献词
- Majesty. - Do read the dedication.
歌颂我最至高无上的君王与夫君
"In praise of my most sovereign lord and husband,
亨利八世
"King Henry VIII,
他不仅心诚志虔博学多识
"Who is not only godly and learned,
而且也是我们的先知摩西
"But who is also our Moses,
因为他将我们从暴君的囚禁
"Since he has delivered us out of the captivity.
与奴役中解放出来
"and bondage of the Pharaoh."
你是指罗马教皇
You mean Rome.
你称教皇的牧师为渣滓
You call the Pope's clergy riffraff,
是教皇安插于其暴政之中的眼线
which he planted in his tyranny?
并将不尽的感激献给我的王与夫君
"And in eternal gratitude to my Lord and husband,
他以卓越功绩向我展示了一条圣洁之路
"Who has shown me by his works a holier path,
将我从我盲目无知的信仰中解救出来
"And delivered me from the ignorance of my blind faith."
凯特 你是当真的吗
Kate. Do you mean this?
没错 陛下 并且这不仅是为我自己
I do, Your Majesty. And not just for myself.
也是为您所有的国民
I mean it for all your subjects.
敬我的夫人
My lady.
赫伯特女士
Lady Herbert.
陛下 加德纳主教求见
Your Majesty. Bishop Gardner is here.
陛下
Majesty.
我欲逮捕并审问一名已知的
I ask permission… to arrest and interrogate a known…
名为安·欧仕培的新教异教徒
Heretic and Protestant called Anne Askew,
因恐其在宫廷有靠山 特请求您的准许
for fear that she has… friends here at Court.
大人 你已获得我的准许
You have my permission, Your Grace.
良善的英国臣民
Good English people.
他们告诉我们
They tell us.
有些人不配
that some of us are not fit to read the words.
阅读我们救世主的文字
of our Saviour and Lord.
我却要说
I say to you,
我宁愿阅读圣经上的文字
I would rather read five lines in the Bible.
也不愿听信寺庙里的惑众妖言
than hear five masses in the temple!
神父声称他能化酒水为上帝之血液
The priest claims to turn the wine into God's blood,
化杂粮为上帝之躯体
and the bread into God's body!
可证据何在
But where is the proof?
自己动手一试真伪吧
Go and find the proof yourself!
将面包放在盒子里三个月
Let the bread lie in the box for three months,
它定将腐烂 毫无可取之处
and it will be mouldy, and so turn to nothing that is good.
让开
Make way!
因此我确信 这绝不是上帝
Wherefore, I am persuaded that it cannot be God!
捉住她
Arrest that woman!
信仰为吾之盾牌 愉悦感染吾之心灵
Faith is my shield. I now rejoice at heart,
信念指引吾之所为
and hope bid me do so,
汝当救吾于灾难
for Thou shall take my part and ease me of my woe!
成吾之欢愉
For Thou art my delight.
主啊 请勿视之…
No face, Lord, to those who look…
萨里大人
My Lord Surrey,
据我们所知 你在圣埃蒂安的战败
it has been put to us that your defeat at Saint-Etienne.
并非如您所说
was not, as you claimed,
当归咎于将士们的无心作战
due to the unwillingness of your soldiers,
而是因你个人的愚蠢
but to your own folly.
以及你的莽撞
And an empty confidence in your own.
和盲目的自大
unreasoning bravery.
对此指控 你有何辩词
How do you answer such a charge?
我想说 此役并非一败涂地
I would answer it was not such a defeat.
其实作战双方都有折损
There was loss and victory on both sides,
而且
and as a matter of fact,
敌人的损失其实更为惨重
the enemy took more losses than we.
即便如此 大人 我们损失却更令人悲痛
Even so, my Lord, our loss was the more grievous,
我们失去了许多将领
since we lost all our captains, who you,
只因你不顾风险
regardless of the danger,
- 将他们派上了前线 - 大人
- sent into the front line. - Your Grace,
我想你从未上过战场吧
I think you were never in battle.
那些军官自愿奔赴前线
Those officers wanted to be in the front line.
一声令下 他们求之不得
They charged with a cry and with greater courage.
奋不顾身 奔赴战场
and in as good an order as anyone would wait for.
他们寡不敌众 却撕开了敌人的防线
They were out numbered, but they broke through the enemy lines.
他们击溃了对方五分之四的防御
They destroyed four-fifths of the convoy.
其时 法军已阵脚大乱
At that moment, the French were in disarray,
若非理事会派给我的人中
and if the few men that this council.
有人临阵退缩
had sent me had not panicked and bolted,
那陛下现在
then His Majesty would now.
应当已在欢庆一场大捷了
be celebrating a great victory.
可是大人 陛下并未迎来胜利
But alas, my Lord, he is not.
你以卵击石
You took a risk in attacking an enemy far superior in numbers,
却最终失败
and you lost.
你私自逃离战场
You were personally forced to flee the battlefield,
理当受罚
which is reprehensible.
在三种情况下 你将被剥夺嘉德爵士头衔
And one of only three ways by which a knight companion.
这便是其中之一
can be degraded from the Order of the Garter.
萨里大人
My Lord Surrey,
我兄弟赫福德大人
my brother, Lord Hertford, has already.
已然指控你
announced allegations against you.
在任职布洛涅副将期间
for corrupt misuse of office while.
贪污受贿 道德腐败
you were Lieutenant General of Boulogne.
他要求立即解除
He has announced an immediate purge on many of those.
你在朝中的各项职务
that you appointed to positions of authority.
大人 相信我
Sir, believe me.
有无数证人能证明
There are just too many witnesses that will tell you.
亨利·霍华德
that Henry Howard was never corrupted.
从未利欲熏心
by personal considerations.
- 也从未收受过贿赂 - 不管怎样
- Nor did his hand ever close upon a bribe. - Nevertheless,
理事会必须解除你的副将一职
this council must confirm your removal as Lieutenant General,
同时也将剥夺你布洛涅统领的头衔
as well as revoke your former title, Captain of Boulogne.
你不可再返回法国
You are ordered not to return to France.
我相信陛下
I'm sure His Majesty will see fit.
一定会收回承命
to countermand these orders.
- 只要让我面见于他 - 大人
- after I have talked with him. - My Lord,
陛下拒绝召见你
His Majesty has refused to grant you an audience.
当真
Has he?
女士
My Lady.
理查·李希先生求见
Sir Richard Rich.
理查先生
Sir Richard.
- 女士 - 您有事相告吗
- Lady Mary. - You have some news?
我很遗憾的通知您 查普维斯先生
I regret to inform you that Eustace Chapuys,
那位曾驻我国的大使
once Imperial Ambassador here, has died,
返回西班牙不久便与世长辞
soon after returning to Spain.
他是位非常卓越的人
He was a remarkable man.
也是位诚挚的朋友
and a true friend.
现在我是孤家寡人了
And… now I have nobody.
玛丽女士
Lady Mary…
我向您保证
Let me assure you.
您在宫中仍有挚友相伴
that you still have many true friends here at Court.
至少还有加德纳主教
Not least, Bishop Gardner.
埃德蒙·伯纳 伦敦主教
And Edmund Bonner, Bishop of London, as well as many others.
以及众多的天主教徒们
who share the Catholic faith.
他们将继续如您般虔诚
Who continue to believe as you believe.
你也一样吗
And you?
是的
Yes.
我可怜的弟弟正被一个异教徒所抚养
My poor brother is being brought up a Protestant and a heretic.
而陛下却丝毫不加阻拦
And the King does nothing to stop it.
请放心
Be assured,
关于此事 我们已有计划
there is work afoot to stop it.
但加德纳大人必须确认
But my Lord Gardner needs to know.
您支持他的行动
that in these works, he has your support…
即使他们也许会伤及您身边的人
Even though they may touch people close to you.
代我向大人问好
Send my love to His Grace.
并转告他 我将为他的成功而祷告
Tell him I will pray fervently for his success.
安·殴仕培
Anne Askew.
- 是的 大人 - 我们听说
- Yes, sir. - We hear that you still.
你仍在当众宣扬邪教
openly, and in public, preach heresy.
大人 我只是在向那些愿意聆听的人
I preach the Word of God, sir.
传达上帝的旨意
To all who will listen.
看来你在宫中有不少朋友
It seems you have friends here at Court.
不过我又想到 你的兄弟曾侍奉过
But then, your brother once served.
国王的家眷
in the King's household, I think.
- 是的 大人 - 我们认为你的这些朋友
- Yes, sir. - We think these friends may include.
也许有些是王后陛下的侍女
some ladies- in- waiting to Her Majesty.
比如 萨福克公爵夫人
The Duchess of Suffolk, for example.
或是王后的姐妹 赫伯特女士
Or Lady Herbert, the Queen's sister.
我们知道你在坐牢期间
We know that you've received monies,
曾收到不少钱 作为救济之用
whilst you've been imprisoned, for your relief.
我们相信
We believe…
是许多身居要职的女士
That diverse important ladies.
给你送的钱
sent you that money.
有个身着蓝色制服的男人
There was a man in a blue coat.
给我送了十先令
who delivered me ten shillings.
他说了什么
And what did he say?
他说 「是赫福德女士给我的」
He said, "My Lady Hertford sent it to me."
是王后许可并支持的吧
With the support and permission of the Queen.
得了吧 欧仕培小姐
Come, come, Mistress Askew!
我们有办法让你开口
We can make you speak.
带她去下面的密室
Have her moved down one level to the chamber.
- 大人 我不能… - 照我们说的做
- Your Grace, I cannot allow… - You will do as we say…
埃德蒙先生
Sir Edmund.
不 不 不
No, no! No!
求求你 求你 求你
Please. Please!Please!
欧仕培小姐
Mistress Askew.
关于布洛涅的事
Your Grace has been badly.
大人您被严重误导了
misinformed as to the events in Boulogne.
我不置可否 大人
I am very prepared to believe it, my Lord.
理事会一而再 再而三地拒绝
Again and again, the Council refused.
我的增援请求
to send reinforcements that I asked for.
连加来的驻守部队也不肯帮忙
Even the garrison at Calais refused to help,
只派了几名笨手笨脚
except to send some flat-footed,
眼歪嘴斜的笨蛋
squint-eyed, unshapely men unfit to carry arms.
现在 我被剥夺了指挥权
And now, my command is revoked.
只是废人一名
Now I am a man of no service.
无计可施
No activity.
还被软禁在家中
And I must sit at home within the walls.
这并非世界末日 大人
Do not think of this as the end of your life, my Lord.
上帝给了您优雅 勇气 和广阔的胸怀
God has given you grace, courage, liberality.
圣埃蒂安一役后
And after Saint-Etienne,
他又赐给了您好运
He also gave you good luck.
幸运之神不过是暂时走开
Luck deserted you for a moment,
但如果一切顺利
but if the rest go on,
您很快会再次为陛下效力
then you will soon serve the King's Majesty again.
完全可以重建声威
And have every chance to regain.
重现昔日荣耀
your honor and reputation.
多谢公爵吉言
I thank your Grace for your words,
但事实是 我一开始于布洛涅带兵
but the truth of it is, I was undermined.
就已遭人陷害 受到攻讦
and attacked from the start of my command in Boulogne.
如今 我敢发誓
And now, I swear to you,
赫福德恨不得取代我的地位
Hertford will smart for usurping my place.
我奉劝大人
I would counsel Your Lordship.
不要与赫福德为敌
not to raise arms against Hertford.
我别无选择
I haven't the choice.
公爵 国王撑不到王子成人
Your Grace, it's sure the King will die.
此事确定无疑
before the Prince reaches his maturity.
那么 将由何人辅佐王子
So who will then govern the Prince…
摄政监国呢
and the realm?
做做样子就好 看在上帝份儿上 小惩就好
Just pinch her, for God's sake. Just pinch her that's all.
别施以酷刑
Nothing more.
我们再问你一次
We ask you again.
王后的哪位侍女
Which of the ladies of Her Majesty's chamber.
对你赠送钱财 并承诺会释放你
sent you monies or promises of relief?
说 王后的哪个侍女
We want to know which of the Queen's Ladies share.
是你的同党
your beliefs.
抑或就是王后本人
Or if the Queen herself does.
- 不见棺材不落泪 - 大人
- We must stretch her further. - My Lords!
对女人用刑
It is absolutely against the King's Law.
这绝对有违国法
to rack a woman!
吾心不忍 不会再继续用刑
And I will do it no further on my conscience.
别激动 埃德蒙大人
Come, come, Sir Edmund.
你很清楚 我们得国王授权
You know perfectly well we have the authority.
- 对她进行审讯 - 陛下会允许你们这样吗
- of the King himself to examine her. - I do not know at all.
恕我不予苟同
that you have His Majesty's permission for this.
我们走
Come!
你这个蠢女人 我问问你
You foolish woman. Let me ask you something.
你认为牧师无法塑造耶稣之身？
Do you say that priests cannot make the body of Christ?
是的 大人
I say so, my Lord.
我只听过上帝创造人
For I have read that God made man.
但人能塑造上帝
But that man can make God,
我至今未曾听说
I have never yet read.
那么祝圣仪式举行后 也不是耶稣之身吗
And after the consecration, is it not the body of Christ?
不 不过是献祭的面包罢了
No. It is but consecrated bread.
如果祝圣仪式后
And what if a mouse eats it.
那东西被老鼠吃了呢
after the consecration?
那老鼠会变成什么呢
What shall become of that mouse?
你认为呢
What say you?
愚蠢的女人
Stupid woman.
我觉得这只老鼠死定了
I say that mouse is damned.
可怜的老鼠
Poor mouse.
- 何事 - 启禀陛下
- What is it? - Your Majesty,
安·欧仕培小姐被无情用刑折磨
I must tell you that the woman Anne Askew.
这绝对是对陛下所制定
has been put to torture in absolute violation.
法律的藐视
of Your Majesty's laws.
你能来找我很好
You were right to come and see me.
如此我便能让你的良心不再内疚
So I may explain to you, and ease your conscience.
若为极端异教
In cases of extreme heresy,
法律并未对男女处罚之别作出规定
the law makes no distinction between a man and a woman.
埃德蒙先生 你该知道
For as you know, Sir Edmund,
魔鬼披着各种外衣
the devil takes many forms.
令人防不胜防
And yet, it is always the devil.
快醒醒
Wake up. Wake up!
王后的事 我们再问你一遍
We desire to ask you again about the Queen.
说吧
Come, now.
快说
Speak, lady.
国王驾到
His Majesty, the King!
（1545年 12月24日 议会）
亲爱的议员们
My well-beloved Commons,
我今日前来
I come here today to speak with you,
对你们阐述心中所想
to set forth my mind.
也对大家敞开心扉
and the secrets of my heart.
这个国家本该纯真有爱
There should be perfect love.
和谐和睦 但是如今
and concord in this realm. But instead,
却纷争不断 争论不休
there is discord and dissention in every place.
在神职人员中 充斥着异教徒和再浸礼教徒
What love and charity is there amongst the clergy.
还有天主教徒和伪君子 他们彼此攻击 互不相让
when one calls the other heretic and Anabaptist?
何来关爱和仁慈可言
And the other calls him Papist and hypocrite?
这就是你们所谓的仁慈吗
Are these tokens of charity amongst you?
这就是你们所谓的手足之爱吗
Are these the signs of fraternal love?
人们向往光明
The people look for light.
而你们令他们陷入黑暗
And you bring them darkness.
至于普通信徒
And as for the laity,
你们的心也被恶意和嫉妒占据
you are not clean of malice and envy,
毁谤责难牧师和主教
for you slander and rebuke priests and bishops.
你们以一己之见
You take it upon yourself to judge the clergy.
靠不切实际的想法和徒劳的解释来
by the sole light of your fantastical opinions.
论断神职人员
and vain expositions.
虽然人人可读圣经
Although you are permitted to read Holy Scripture,
但你们必须清楚 当在许可范围内
you must understand that it is under license.
并且要对得起自己的良心
and only to inform your conscience.
而不是制造争端 曲解圣经
Not to dispute and make scripture.
你们对圣经可以有自己的理解
I gave you the Bible in your own tongue,
但很遗憾 这件最珍贵的东西
but I am sorry to see that most precious jewel,
上帝之言
the Word of God,
在这个国家的各个酒肆客栈
has been disputed, rhymed,
被质疑 被改写传唱 人们大吵大闹
sung and jangled in every alehouse and every tavern in this realm.
本人
I,
作为上帝指定的教皇
whom God has appointed his Vicar here,
不愿再见到这种纷争
will see these divisions extinct,
希望那些暴行得到修正
and those enormities corrected.
不然 上帝讲视我为无用的仆人
Or God shall account me an unprofitable servant.
所以
Therefore…
大家应当 宽厚待人
Be of charity with one another,
亲如兄弟
like brother and brother.
作为
Love,
你们至高无上的君主 我劝诫你们
dread, and serve God, to which I, as your supreme head,
要敬爱上帝 畏惧上帝 侍奉上帝
and sovereign Lord exhort and require you.
我此前所言之仁爱友善
And I doubt not, but that love and affinity which.
将永存于世 永不消亡
I spoke of at the beginning shall never be dissolved.
我确信无疑
or broken between us.
国王所言何事 托马斯先生
What did the King say, Sir Thomas?
他震怒于国内宗教分裂之事
He was angry with the religious divisions in his realm.
他说允许人们解读圣经
He said that he gave people the Bible to read,
并非让人任意曲解其意
but not so that they could dispute its meanings.
对我来说 陛下的举动就好似
It seems to me like His Majesty is like one.
将一个人掷出高塔 在他坠落之时
who would throw a man headlong off the top of a high tower.
却要求他中途停下
and ask him to stop when he is halfway down.
可以肯定的是 宣扬罗马暴政及盲目的信仰
But surely, our delivery from the tyranny of Rome and blind faith.
不会是改革以及
is not the end of the Reform.
基督徒复兴的结束
and the renewal of our Christian life,
而仅仅是个开始
but it is only the beginning.
国王确实认为他是唯一了解上帝意志的人
The King does suppose that only he knows the Will of God,
所以 虽然不切实际
and so whatever he thinks should therefore be the new Orthodoxy,
他的想法即为新的正教
however fantastical.
仿佛他的个人宗教信仰一般
It is like his own private religion.
另外 他要求仁爱和宽厚
And yet, he asks for an end to division for charity and love.
托马斯先生 他仍旧是国王
Sir Thomas, he is still the King.
若他提出仁爱和宽厚
And if he asks for charity and love,
那么他就是在执行上帝的意愿
then he is doing no more than Christ did.
陛下 国王已经打开了潘多拉的盒子
Madam, the King has opened a Pandora's Box.
不管他愿意与否
And whether he will or not,
抱怨几多 盒子一旦打开 便再难合上
he simply cannot close it now, whatever his complaints.
你有心事 在担心什么
You look troubled. What is it?
我从未像现在这般担心
I fear now, more than ever, the machinations of men.
小人的阴谋诡计 将会如何影响朝廷和国王
How their plots and plans swirl about the Court and the King.
我能觉察得到 却心有余而力不足
I can sense it, but I have no knowledge anymore.
除了国王 似乎所有人都疏远于我
No one, it seems, least of all the King, confides in me.
这样不好吗
But is it not better so?
有利有弊
In some ways,
我有更多时间陪伴你
since it leaves me free to love you at my leisure.
但话说回来 这也让我能远离政务
But in other ways, it condemns my high station.
特别是现在
to neglect affairs of the realm, especially now.
小人用阴谋保障将来和他们的利益
Men conspire to secure his future, and their own profit.
我不明白
But I don't understand.
如何保障将来
How can they secure the future?
把王子当做傀儡
By controlling the Prince.
大家都认为国王的健康每况愈下
It's widely supposed that the King's infirmities grow worse.
从而无法活着看到王子成年
And he will not live to see the Prince come to maturity.
你还爱着国王吗
Do you still love the King?
- 赫福德大人 - 陛下
- My Lord Hertford. - Majesty.
法兰西那边情况如何
So. There is peace with France.
国王陛下只有接受合约
Only if Your Majesty accepts the terms.
什么合约
What are the terms?
陛下必须在八年内
In 8 years' time,
归还布洛涅
Your Majesty will hand back Boulogne.
法国方面会支付两百万克朗
In return… for a payment of 2 million crowns.
- 两百万 - 是的 陛下
- 2 million? - Yes, Your Majesty.
法国统帅 克劳德·达奈博
The Admiral of France, Claude d'Annibault,
会亲自前来宫廷签署合约
will come here to Your Majesty's court to sign the peace treaty.
如果国王陛下首肯
If Your Majesty so desires.
国王陛下
Your Majesty?
干得不错 赫福德大人
You've done well, my Lord Hertford.
告退
Majesty.
- 大人 - 陛下
- My Lord. - Majesty.
加德纳主教大人审问了安·欧仕培 那个异教徒
His Grace, Bishop Gardner, having examined the heretic Anne Askew,
特此前来得到陛下允许
requests Your Majesty's permission to order the arrests of three.
以逮捕王后陛下的三位侍女
of Her Majesty's ladies.
其中包括她的妹妹 赫伯特女士
Including Her Majesty's sister, lady Herbert.
主教大人须就她们私藏禁书
His Grace would like to question them as to their knowledge.
和异端思想 对其进行询问
and keeping of forbidden materials.
怎么
What?
- 守住门口 - 是 大人
- Stay at the door. - Yes, my Lord.
先生们
Gentlemen.
- 大人 - 大人
- My Lord. - My Lord.
这是一项伟大的事业
Here is a very great undertaking,
你我的命运都悬于此
upon which our lives will depend.
但我们首先必须决定
But what we must first decide is.
接近温莎的最佳途径
how best to approach Windsor…
并击退保护王子的守卫
and in what manner to overcome the guards that surround the Prince.
接着我们带走王子
And so, remove him.
毫无疑问 先生们
For, be in no doubt, gentlemen,
只要控制了王位继承人
that he who possesses the heir to the throne.
那么王位也就不在话下
will very soon possess the throne itself.
王后陛下驾到
Her Majesty, the Queen!
- 莱斯利大人 - 陛下
- My Lord Risley. - Your Majesty.
- 主教大人 - 王后陛下
- Your Grace. - Your Majesty.
- 我能跳舞吗 - 当然了 我的好小姐
- May I dance? - Of course you may, my Lady.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
- 王后陛下 - 赫福德大人
- Your Majesty. - My Lord Hertford.
见您从法国归来 我倍感欣喜
I am most glad to see you returned from France.
谢谢 陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
加德纳主教逮捕了我妹妹
Bishop Gardner has arrested my sister.
还有两名侍女 怀疑她们是异教徒
and two of my ladies on suspicion of heresy.
- 主教大人 - 玛丽公主
- Your Grace. - Lady Mary.
你的调查进展如何
How go your investigations?
一切顺利
They go well.
我们在王后侍女的橱柜内
For we have discovered certain books.
发现了几本异端邪说书籍
in the closets of the Queen's ladies,
之后会对她们进一步问讯
about which they will be questioned further.
那个异教徒 安·欧仕培呢
And the heretic, Anne Askew?
我很高兴地告诉您 玛丽公主
Ah, well I'm happy to tell, good lady,
国王陛下下令
that on His Majesty's orders, she is condemned.
她将在伦敦肉市场被处以火刑
to be burned at Smithfield.
逮捕他
Seize him!
萨里大人 你以叛国罪被捕
My Lord Surrey, you are under arrest for treason.
新鲜好吃的肉
Sweetmeats. Fresh meats!
走过路过不要错过
Come on in, everyone!
- 这位先生 - 你有何事 夫人
- Sir. Sir. - What does he want, my Lady?
给
Here.
把这个绑在她脖子上
Tie this around her neck.
好让她早点解脱
It will end her suffering quickly.
拜托了
Take it.
不止看在钱的份上
Not just for the money,
还为了上帝的仁爱
But also for the love of God.
赫福德夫人
My Lady Hertford.
有何贵干
What do you want?
只是前来通知 加德纳主教要见您
Just to let you know that Bishop Gardner would like to see you.
越快越好
Very soon.
这是什么
What's this?
火药
Gunpowder.
一个朋友的礼物
Gift from a friend.
萨里大人
My Lord Surrey.
若是国王驾崩
If the King should die,
年幼的王子无力执掌朝政
leaving the Lord Prince at his tender age, have you either.
你是否有策划或暗示过 摄政的人选呢
devised or suggested who should govern him in this realm?
无论怎样
Whether that is,
在此种情形下
you have ever said that in such a case,
你是否说过由自己来摄政
you would have the rule and governance of him?
抑或是相似的话语
Or words to that effect?
好吧 奈维特表弟 我明白你的意思
Yes, yes, cousin Knyvit. I understood the question.
还有 你是否蓄意佩戴
Also, is it true that you willfully bear the Royal Arms.
忏悔者爱德华国王的王家纹章
of King Edward the Confessor?
并声称自己是他的继任或亲属
And claim to be the next heir or kin to him?
以我的身份和血统 我确有这个权力
I only put in my coat of arms what I am entitled to put there,
理查德爵士
Sir Richard.
我来告诉你吧 萨里大人
I'll tell you this, my Lord Surrey,
若是你的确掌握权力
if ever you got power here, in this realm,
我便会选择离开此地
I would go abroad and stay there.
因为我是如此惧怕于你的怨念
Because I would be so afraid of your malice.
奈维特表弟 我的怨念不在于你如此卑微之徒
Cousin Knyvit, I am maliced not so low as you.
而是在于身居高位之人
My malice goes much higher.
他说他怨恨身居高位之人
He said his malice went even higher?
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
据线报称 萨里和他的党徒们的目的
My informants tell me that it was the intention of Surrey.
在于谋杀议会所有成员
and his associates to usurp authority by means of the murder.
并以此进行篡位
of all members of the Council,
由他们掌控王子
and the control of the Prince by them alone.
居然如此用心险恶
God forbid they should have succeeded.
- 天诛地灭 - 陛下所言极是
- in their abominable enterprise! - Yes, Your Majesty.
上帝保佑 我们及时发现
Thank God the whole was found out.
我过去如此爱他
I used to love him.
是的 我深知他骄傲而愚蠢
Yes, I've always known he was proud.
但我并不在意 依然这么爱他
and foolish. But I loved him for all that.
但他却辜负了我的爱
Now he has forfeited my love.
- 马丁 - 大人
- Martin. - My Lord.
- 带匕首了吗 - 是的 大人
- Did you get the dagger? - Yes, my Lord.
好样的
Good man.
过来
Come over here.
下面是条河
That's the river.
涨潮时分会涌上来
It comes right up at high tide.
我正好能从这个井里跳下去 我确定
I can just about fit down the shaft, I'm certain.
走吧 到圣凯瑟琳码头
Go now, to St. Catherine's dock,
弄一艘船 在那儿等我
get a boat. Wait for me there.
我午夜时分应该能到
I should be with you by midnight.
看在上帝份上 马丁 要是我没能成功
For the love of God, Martin, do as I ask,
- 就照我说的做 - 是 大人
- for if I do not escape from this place… - Yes, my Lord.
妹妹 过来 别哭了
Sister. There, there! Weep no more.
你被释放了 他们没有证据
You were released! Nothing has been found.
一切都会好起来的
Everything is going to be all right.
相信我
Believe me.
一切都会好起来
Everything is going to be all right.
亲爱的安 你没事了
Darling Anne, you're safe.
你没事了
You're safe.
关门
Close the door!
他要逃跑 快来人
He's escaping! Help me!
诸位大人 陪审团成员
My Lords, members of the jury.
伯爵犯下的诸多罪行
For either of the offenses the Earl has committed,
理应死罪
he deserves death.
首先 肆意佩戴王家纹章
First, for usurping the Royal Arms,
并有篡夺王位之嫌
which gives rise to the suspicion that he hoped to become King.
其次 他企图越狱
The other, for escaping from prison,
- 恰恰证明他心里有鬼 - 你错了
- whereby he proved his guilt. - You are false!
见钱眼开 甚至能出卖自己的父亲
And to earn a piece of gold, would condemn your own father!
我从未试图盗取王家纹章
I never sought to usurp the King's Arms.
众所周知 我的祖先们本来就有
For everyone knows my ancestors bore them!
去诺福克的教堂吧 你自然会看到
Go to the church in Norfolk. You will see them there.
五百年来 一直如此
For they have been ours for 500 years.
注意你的言辞 大人
Hold your peace, my Lord!
- 你是意图叛国和篡夺王位 - 那你呢
- Your idea was to commit treason and become King! - And you!
尔等鼠辈
You cats pole!
你有什么资格出此狂言
What have you to do with it?
你还是给我闭上嘴吧
You had better hold your tongue!
自从国王在朝廷中任用尔等奸佞小人
For this kingdom has never been well since the King put.
英格兰就一直鸡飞狗跳 民不聊生
mean creatures like you into this government!
法庭上请保持肃静
Silence in court!
肃静
Silence!
假若如你所说 指控并不属实
If, as you say, the accusations are false,
你可否解释 为何企图逃离伦敦塔
can you explain to us why you tried to escape the Tower?
我当时就是为避免
I tried to escape to prevent myself from.
陷入此种境地
coming to the pass in which I am now.
至于你 大人 当然心知肚明
And you, my Lord, well know.
人非圣贤 孰能无过
that no matter how right a man may be,
欲加之罪 何患无辞
they always find the fallen one guilty.
你落得今日之田地 大人
You have only yourself to blame, my Lord,
- 怨不得别人 - 不
- for the pass you're in. - No.
只是朋友变敌人
It was a friendly foe.
善意得恶报
My shadow of good will.
谁能料到老伙计和好朋友会设计害我
My old companion and dear friend that trapped me.
- 亨利·霍华德 请作最后陈述 - 无罪
- Henry Howard. How do you plead? - Not guilty.
凭据何在
How will you be tried?
苍天可鉴 国民为证
By God, and the country.
我确实憎恨伯爵
I knew that I hated the Earl.
但令我惊讶的是 理查德爵士 你也如此
But I am surprised, Sir Richard, that you share my antipathy.
赫福德大人 没必要如此惊讶
My Lord Hertford, you should not be so surprised,
因为伯爵同样憎恨我们
since the Earl hates us both the same.
所以我肯定…
So I am sure…
解决掉他 对你我都大有裨益
all of us will prosper better without him.
我赞同
I agree.
大人们 打扰了
My Lords, forgive me.
身为陪审团主席 我有必要告诉各位大人
But as foreman of the jury, I have to tell your Lordships.
控告萨里大人谋反一案 证据不足
that we are not impressed with the evidence against my Lord Surrey.
我们都很清楚
It is very clear to us.
萨里大人有权佩戴
that my Lord Surrey has the right to bear the arms.
忏悔者爱德华的纹章 至于谋反一事
of Edward the Confessor. And as to the plot against His Majesty,
尚无可靠的证据支持
we can find no credible evidence to support it.
先生们
Sirs…
我们一致认为 伯爵因此等琐事遭受指控
We do not think it right and proper that the Earl should.
实在是不该
be condemned for such… trifles.
克里斯托弗阁下 既然国王已经认定
Sir Christopher, whenever has innocence.
他应该以死谢天下
been cause to save a man's life.
他还能借口清白无辜 从而死里逃生吗
when the King deems him unfit to live in the Commonwealth?
大人 这是基于律法的审判
My Lord. This is a trial under law.
海登大人
Master Hayden,
假如你并不清楚 那么我来告诉你
if you did not know it before, then you know it now.
所谓律法也就是陛下的意愿
The law is whatever His Majesty says it is.
如果你惹恼了陛下
And if you provoke His Majesty,
你也会吃不了兜着走
then you, too, will feel the full force of it.
你怎么了 玛丽公主 不舒服吗
What is wrong, Lady Mary? Are you unwell?
没有 夫人
No, Madam.
那是为何
Then?
我听闻一些流言
I have heard some rumors.
关于何事 玛丽公主
Rumors about what, Lady Mary?
新上任的罗马帝国大使告诉我
The new Imperial Ambassador has told me.
在安特卫普以及国外有传言说
that in Antwerp and in other foreign places,
国王正在物色新的妻子
that they are saying the King is looking for a new wife.
他们为何这么说
Why should they say so?
你们结婚已有时日
Despite the length of your marriage,
你却未给陛下添丁
you have still not presented His Majesty with a child.
玛丽公主
Lady Mary.
我们曾亲密无间 你还记得吗
We were such good friends. You remember that, don't you?
对我而言 一切都没变
Well, for me, nothing has changed.
我爱你 一如既往
And I love you, as I did before.
不过 世事变迁
But something has happened,
你对我已大不如从前
and you no longer love me as you did before.
为何
Why?
陪审团的诸位先生们
Gentlemen of the jury,
请你们陈述审判意见
how do you find the defendant?
有罪
Guilty!
他要以死谢罪
And he should die for it!
你们凭什么判断我有罪
Of what have you found me guilty?
很显然 你们没有
Surely, there is no law.
法律依据 但我知道
that justifies you. But I know the King.
国王想铲除身边所有的贵族
wants to get rid of all the noble blood around him.
只用低贱之人
And employ none but low people.
- 无罪 - 判决造假
- Not guilty! - This trial is a sham!
- 真差劲 - 亨利·霍华德
- No chop, chop! - Henry Howard…
释放他
Release him!
你被判遣返原籍
You will be taken to the place from whence you came,
在伦敦游街示众
and there, to be dragged through the city of London.
押至泰伯恩受刑
unto the place of execution called Tyburn!
先受绞刑 待濒死之时
There, to be hanged, cut down while still alive,
阉其下体 剜其五脏
your privy parts cut off, and your bowels taken out.
焚烤其身
of your body and burned before you.
斩其首级 大卸四块
Your head cut off, and your body divided into four parts.
碎尸置于何处
The head and the quarters to be set at such places.
将由国王指定
as the King shall assign.
国王在哪里 这完全是乱来
Where's the King? This is a travesty!
所谓乐活便是
The happy life be these:
心静如止水
The quiet mind,
君子坦荡荡
the equal friend,
小人长戚戚
no grudge, no strife,
大智从率直
wisdom joined with simplicity,
长夜无愁绪
the night discharged of all care.
国王在哪里
Where's the King?
- 谢谢 莱斯利大人 - 逆贼未能得逞
- Thank you, lord Risley. - The King is saved from conspirators.
至于安·欧仕培…
And Anne Askew…
宝贝 我听说你近来钻进了书堆里
Sweetheart? I hear you've been busying yourself with your books.
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
我翻译了伊拉斯谟的著作
I have translated works by Erasmus,
还买了一本好书 托马斯·贝莱特的圣咏集
as well as buying a beautiful book of psalms by Thomas Berthelet.
我很惊讶 凯特 你竟如此勤奋
I wonder, Kate, at your diligence.
我视其为责任 同时也感到荣幸
Well, I regard it as much my duty as my pleasure,
能将如此好书
to place such wonderful books.
献给善良的英国人民 长久以来
before the good English people who have been a long time.
他们一直渴望着来自圣经的
thirsting and hungering for the sincere.
真知灼见 金玉良言
and plain knowledge of God's Word.
小心为上
Just be cautious.
并非每个英国人都能阅读并理解福音书
Not every English person can read or understand the Gospels.
此事产生的影响难以预料
And you are to be careful of the consequences.
- 须谨慎对待 - 陛下
- of encouraging them to try. - Majesty,
我不惧怕福音书 谁都不应该如此
I am not afraid of the Gospels, nor should anyone be afraid.
陛下着手肃清来自罗马的荒谬信仰
Your Majesty has begun a great work in banishing.
实乃丰功伟业
the monstrous idol of Rome.
如今有神相助
And now with God's help,
您定能彻底清除
you can finish that work.
英国教会的余孽
by purging the Church of England of its dregs.
- 陛下 - 抱歉 我累了
- Majesty… - Forgive me. I am tired.
告退 陛下
Majesty.
凯特
Kate.
- 告退 陛下 - 告退 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
- Majesty. - Majesty.
- 告退 陛下 - 告退 陛下
- Majesty. - Your Majesty.
告退 陛下
Your Majesty.
这算怎么回事 女人也来评点国事
What a thing it is, when women become such clerks,
还振振有词地教训一通
and what a comfort it will be to me in my old age.
欺负朕年老力衰吗
to be lectured to by my wife.
陛下无需受人教导
Your Majesty has no need to be taught by anyone.
您的神学知识日益精进 远胜王公贵族
Your knowledge of divinity excels that of the princes.
乃至教徒神父
and divines throughout the ages.
恕我直言 臣以为
Forgive me, but I think it unseemly.
身为臣民 不可与陛下如此争执
for any of your subjects to argue with you,
王后也不能例外 陛下
as the Queen has just done. Majesty,
曾有多少位高权重之人
many of the greatest subjects in the land.
因为散播异端邪说
defending those same arguments that she does.
而被依法处死
have, by law, deserved death.
你没有证据 竟然就敢指控王后
I cannot believe that you would accuse the Queen of heresy.
散播邪说
without proof.
我有证据
I have the proof.
但我需要陛下首肯
But what I need is Your Majesty's consent.
许我草拟一份声讨王后的诉状
to draw up certain articles against the Queen,
如此才能依法审案
so that she may be put on trial.
让她受审吧
She could be put on trial.
但是 朕要饶她不死
And yet, I am fully resolved to spare her life.
当然
Certainly.
如陛下所愿
Whatever Your Majesty desires.